Register of the Charles MacArthur Carman, Jedburgh Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles MacArthur Carman, Jedburgh Collection
1934-1994
90090
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 envelope, 2 microfilm reels (5.5 linear feet)
Reports, orders, letters, writings, printed matter, and audiovisual material, relating to Jedburgh operations carried out by the Office of Strategic Services in 1944, involving parachuting operatives behind German lines in the Netherlands, Belgium and France to effect liaison with local resistance forces. Includes copies of official records of the operations, and subsequent recollections of veterans of the operations. Some materials are photocopies. In part, originals are located in the National Archives and Records Administration.
Carman, Charles MacArthur, collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Some materials are photocopies. In part, originals are located in the National Archives and Records Administration.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Charles MacArthur Carman collection in the Hoover Institution Archives consists primarily of materials relating to the activities of the Office of Strategic Services in the last phase of World War II, and specifically to the operations of the Jedburgh teams that were parachuted into German-occupied areas of Holland, Belgium, and France in 1944.
The three man Jedburgh teams, which were made up of American, British, Dutch, and French agents, attempted to reinforce and coordinate local resistance activities against German forces in advance of the Allied offensive that followed the Normandy landings in June 1944. They trained and armed resistance forces, undertook sabotage actions, and attacked German troops. A number of Jedburgh team members were killed in action or executed by the Germans.
The bulk of the collection is comprised of photocopies of military records located in the National Archives in Washington, D.C. In addition, there are publications and other materials collected by Charles MacArthur Carman, who was himself a former Jedburgh agent (a member of team Maurice). Many of these concern the history of the French resistance, often at the level of a specific region or town (see Printed Matter series).
In later years, Carman corresponded with other former Jedburgh operatives, and this correspondence, where it appears, is identified. The collection also includes a number of photographs of Jedburgh training exercises and videorecordings of commemorations of the Normandy landings and of Jedburgh operations. Additionally, there are two examples of items carried by Jedburgh operatives, a map and code chart, both printed on silk (see Oversize Materials).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: Office of Strategic Services File, Printed Matter, Photographs, Sound Recordings, Video Recordings, Oversize Materials, and Microfilm.
United States. Office of Strategic Services.; Secret service--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Belgium.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Netherlands.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.
- Office of Strategic Services File, 1934-1991. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Numerical files, Jedburgh "after action" reports, and files relating to specific individuals, arranged separately
  - Numerical files relating to Jedburgh operations, 1944-1991
    - Unnumbered. Letter from John P. Bodnar to Colonel Cheever, 1987 December 13 (Folder 1: 1)
    - No. 31. "Remembering Jedburgh Team Augustus" by Paul Ausseresses, with accompanying letter to Captain Irwin, 1989 October 25. (Folder 1: 2)
      Holograph
    - No. 32. Printed copy of an obituary of Christopher Blathwayt, 1990 (Folder 1: 3)
    - No. 33. "Journey of a Jed" by Stanley Cannicott, undated. (Folder 1: 4)
      Typescript
    - No. 34. Holograph excerpt, "Chapitre V--L'évasion," undated, and newsletters published by the organization Amicale du bataillion charollais, 1984-1985 (Folder 1: 5)
    - No. 36. Guidebook, Musée de la Résistance et de la Déportation, Besançon, France, undated (Folder 1: 6)
    - No. 37. Printed copy of obituary of Dom Joseph Coombe-Tennant, The Times(London), 1989 November 14 (Folder 1: 7)
    - No. 38. Printed copy of Debout les paras, 1990 September-October (Folder 1: 8)
    - No. 39. Typescript of memorandum by George A. Schriever, 1944 December 4 (Folder 1: 9)
    - No. 40. Two letters relating to a memorial fund in honor of Horace W. Fuller, 1990 (Folder 1: 10)
    - No. 41. Postcard addressed to Charles Carman, with enclosure, an excerpt from Le Finistère dans la guerre, 1989 July 31 (Folder 1: 11)
    - No. 42. Typescript, "Report on Seventy-five SO Agents (Mostly Jedburghs) Dropped by Parachute into France,", undated. (Folder 1: 12)
    - No. 131. Photocopy of cartoon by Victor A. Gough, with accompanying biographical information, undated. (Folder 1: 13)
    - No. 133. Two letters to Charles M. Carman from Wyman W. Irwin, 1990-1991, and typescript of paper by Irwin, "Jedburgh Operations in Southeast France, June 1944--January 1945,", 1990 May 14 (Folder 1: 14)
    - No. 134. Materials relating to Jedburgh operations sent to Charles M. Carman by Michael R. King. Typescript, "Rapport du Team 'Ian'," 1944 September 26, and correspondence, 1991 (Folder 1: 15)
    - No. 135. Typescript of thesis by William W. Irwin, "A Special Force: Origin and Development of the Jedburgh Project in Support of Operation Overlord,", 1991 (Folder 1: 16)
    - No. 136. Printed copy of Le maquis de Beaubery et le bataillon du Charollais by Claude Zeigel, 1947 (Folder 1: 17)
    - No. 137
      - Typescript of paper by S. J. Lewis, "Jedburgh Team Operations in Support of the 12th Army Group, August 1944,", 1987 July (Folder 1: 18)
      - Typescript of translation of "The England Spiel (England Maneouvre)" by J. E. van der Starp, 1948 (Folder 1: 19)
    - No. 138. Typescript, "The Springing Tigers in France, 1944" by R. G. Loosmore, 1985 May (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - No. 139. Excerpt from Vercors, haut-lieu de France by Pierre Tenant, 1966 (Folder 2: 2)
    - No. 140. Letter from Henry D. McIntosh to Charles M. Carman, with enclosures, 1990 August 27 (Folder 2: 3)
    - No. 141. Excerpt from Guide des maquis et hauts-lieux de la Résistance d'Auvergne by Gilles Lévy, undated. (Folder 2: 4)
    - No. 142. Typescript report on Operation Linnet, 1944 August 29 (Folder 2: 5)
    - No. 231. Letter from Roger Meuret to Charles M. Carman, with enclosures, 1991 May 20 (Folder 2: 6)
    - No. 232. Typescript, "Reminiscences of a Junior SOE Officer: C'est magnifique mais ce n'est pas la guerre, or How the 'Maquis' Really Was--for Some,", undated. (Folder 2: 7)
    - No. 233. Excerpt from Les fougères de la liberté, 1939-1945 by Emilienne Eychenne, undated. (Folder 2: 8)
    - No. 234. Letter from John M. Olmsted to Charles M. Carman, with enclosure, 1990 March 5 (Folder 2: 9)
    - No. 235. Typescript, "About the Jedburghs," 1982 Fall, and correspondence relating to citations and awards given to members of Jedburgh teams, 1945 April 12 (Folder 2: 10)
    - No. 236. Typescript, "Raw Interrogation: 'Fife and Carlow',", 1944 July 28 (Folder 2: 11)
    - No. 237. Excerpt from Mémorial de la Résistance en Haute-Savoie, undated. (Folder 2: 12)
    - No. 238. Contents transferred to Photographs series (Folder 2: 13)
    - No. 239. Letter from Michel Boissarie to Charles M. Carman, with enclosure, 1991 June 2 (Folder 2: 14)
    - No. 240. Thesis, "The Jedburghs: Combat Operations Conducted in the Finistère Region of Brittany, France from July--September 1944" by Elliot J. Rosner, 1990 (Folder 2: 15)
    - No. 241. Printed copy of pamphlet, Septembre 1944, le VIe corps U.S. libère Besançon, undated. (Folder 2: 16)
    - No. 242. Typescript report relating to Jedburgh operation Comet, 1944 September 7 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Jedburgh "after action" reports, and related materials, arranged by name of team or mission, 1944-1990
    - Alan. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Alastair. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Alec. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 20)
    - Alexander. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 21)
    - Alfred. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 22)
    - Ammonia. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 23)
    - Andrew. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 24)
    - Andy. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 25)
    - Anthony. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 2: 26)
    - Archibald. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 27)
    - Arnold. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 28)
    - Arthur. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 29)
    - Aubrey. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 30)
    - Auguste. Two typescript reports, 1944; one typescript speech, 1984 September 9; and one letter, 1989 October 20 (Folder 2: 31)
    - Basil. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 32)
    - Benjamin and Bernard. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 33)
    - Brian. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 2: 34)
    - Bruce. Typescript, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Bugatti. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Bunny. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Cecil. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Cedric. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Chloroform. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Chrysler. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Cinnamon. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 8)
    - Citroen. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 9)
    - Clarence. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 10)
    - Claude. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Collodion. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Daniel I. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Daniel II. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Desmond. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Dodge. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Douglas I and Douglas II. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 17)
    - Dudley. Typescript report, 1944, and typescript manuscript, undated. (Folder 3: 18)
    - Edward. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Ephedrine. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 20)
    - Felix. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 21)
    - Francis. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 22)
    - Frank. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 3: 23)
    - Frederick. Typescript, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Gavin. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 4: 2)
    - George I. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 3)
    - George II. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Gerald. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Gilbert. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Giles. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Godfrey. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Gregory. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Guy. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Hamish. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 11)
    - Harold. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 12)
    - Harry. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Henry. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Hilary. Typescript report, 1944. (Folder 4: 15)
      Also includes a typescript account by E. Mautaint, 1984, and photocopy of a print depicting a monument commemorating team Hilary, 1990
    - Horace. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 16)
    - Hugh. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 17)
    - Ian. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 18)
    - Ivor. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 19)
    - Jacob. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 20)
    - James. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 21)
    - Jeremy. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 4: 22)
    - Jim. Typescript, 1944 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - John. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Jude. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Julian. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Lee. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Mark. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Martin. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Masque. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Maurice. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 9)
    - Miles. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Minaret. One typescript report, 1944, and one letter, 1944 October 1 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Monocle. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 12)
    - Nicholas. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 13)
    - Norman. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 14)
    - Novocaine. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 15)
    - Packard. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 16)
    - Paul. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 17)
    - Philip. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 18)
    - Quentin. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 19)
    - Quinine. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 20)
    - Raymond. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 21)
    - Roderick. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 22)
    - Ronald. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 23)
    - Sceptre. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 24)
    - Scion. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 25)
    - Simon. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 26)
    - Stanley I. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 27)
    - Stanley II. Two typescript reports, 1944 (Folder 5: 28)
    - Timothy. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 5: 29)
    - Tony. Typescript, 1944 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Veganine. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Verveine. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Willys. Typescript, 1944 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Files relating to specific individuals involved in Jedburgh operations, 1934-1990
    - Galbert, Maurice de (nom de guerre, Jacques Le Rocher). Correspondence, identity cards, and pay book, 1934-1966 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Lajeunesse, Lucien E. Correspondence, identity card, and program, 1943-1951 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Olmsted, John M. Clippings, correspondence and reports
      - 1943 (Folder 6: 7)
      - 1944 (Folder 6: 8-9)
      - 1945 (Folder 6: 10)
      - 1987-1990 (Folder 6: 11)
    - Péré, Pierre. Brochure, map, postcard, and reports, 1987 (Folder 6: 12)
  - Printed Matter, 1944-1994.
    Brochures and leaflets; monographs; and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by physical form
    - Brochures and leaflets
      - 1945-1989 (Folder 6: 13)
      - 1991-1994 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Monographs
      - undated. (Folder 7: 2-4)
      - 1944 (Folder 7: 5)
      - 1945 (Folder 7: 6)
      - 1948 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Serial issues, 1994 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Photographs, 1944-1994.
    Arranged chronologically
    - Five prints depicting Jedburgh training exercises, England, circa 1944 (Folder 7: 9)
    - Four prints depicting Jedburgh training courses, Milton Hall, England, circa 1944 (Folder 7: 10)
      (Originally contained in numerical file no. 238)
    - One print depicting a victory parade, France, circa 1944 (Folder 7: 11)
    - Two prints depicting the grave of Captain T. A. Mellows, France, 1991 (Folder 7: 12)
    - Two prints depicting a monument to Captain T. A. Mellows, France, 1991 (Folder 7: 13)
    - Two prints depicting a street named for Captain T. A. Mellows, France, 1991 (Folder 7: 14)
    - One print depicting a plaque commemorating Commonwealth soldiers, France, 1991 (Folder 7: 15)
    - Four prints depicting a ceremony inaugurating a plaque in honor of the Jedburgh operations, United States, 1994 January 28 (Folder 7: 16)
    - One print depicting General William J. Donovan and Lucien E. Lajeunesse, 1944 December 15 (Box 10 A.V.)
  - Sound Recordings, 1994. (Box 8)
    Compact and mini sound cassettes, arranged chronologically
    - One compact sound cassette, "L'Épopée du Vercors,", undated. (Folder 8: 1)
    - Four mini sound cassettes containing interviews relating to Jedburgh operations, 1994 (Folder 8: 2-5)
  - Video Recordings, 1994.
    VHS videocassettes, arranged chronologically
    - One VHS videocassette, "Musée de la Résistance Bretonne,", undated. (Folder 8: 1)
    - One VHS videocassette labeled "Égletons, E.N.P.I.,", 1994 (Folder 8: 2)
    - One VHS videocassette labeled "Josselin/ Cöetquidan/Égletons, E.N.P. II,", 1994 (Folder 8: 3)
    - One VHS videocassette labeled "Neuvic,", 1994 (Folder 8: 4)
    - One VHS videocassette labeled "Solstice en Provence,", 1994 (Folder 8: 5)
    - One VHS videocassette labeled "Eliz/Omaha, Running-In,", 1994 (Folder 8: 6)
    - One VHS videocassette containing footage of the dedication ceremony for a plaque in memory of the Jedburgh operations, 1994 January 28 (Folder 8: 7)
    - One VHS videocassette containing scenes of the Musée de la Résistance bretonne, St. Marcel, France, and other places associated with the 1944 liberation of France, 1994 June-August (Folder 8: 8)
    - One VHS videocassette containing footage of the 50th anniversary commemoration of the Normandy landings, 1994 June 5-11 (Folder 8: 9)
    - One VHS videocassette labeled "Omaha,", 1994 June 6 (Folder 8: 10)
  - Oversize Materials, 1944-1983. (Box 9)
    Map, chart, photocopies, brochure, and clippings, arranged by physical form
    - One map printed on silk depicting regions of Holland, Belgium, France, and Germany, circa 1944 (Folder 9: 1)
    - One set of codes printed on silk, circa 1944 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Photocopies of photographs depicting bomb damage at Égletons, France, 1944 August (Folder 9: 3)
    - Brochure and clippings relating to the French resistance group Bolambo, 1983 (Folder 9: 3)
- Microfilm Cabinet Microfilm, undated.
  Two reels of filmed records from the National Archives of the United States